<PAGE>
	<INCLUDE file="inc/header.tmpl" />

	<VAR match="VAR_SEL_PROTOCOLS" replace="selected" />
	<VAR match="VAR_SEL_FORTINET" replace="selected" />
	<PARSE file="menu1.xml" />
	<PARSE file="menu2-protocols.xml" />

	<INCLUDE file="inc/content.tmpl" />

<h1>Fortinet SSL VPN</h1>

<p>Experimental support for <a
href="https://www.fortinet.com/products/vpn">Fortinet SSL
VPN</a> was added to OpenConnect in March 2021. It is also known as FortiGate
in some documentation. It is a
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Point-to-Point_Protocol">PPP</a>-based
protocol using the native PPP support which was merged into the 9.00
release.</p>

<p>Fortinet mode is requested by adding <tt>--protocol=fortinet</tt>
to the command line:
<pre>
  openconnect --protocol=fortinet fortigate.example.com
</pre></p>

<h2>Quirks and Issues</h2>

<p>In terms of authentication for Fortinet VPNs, OpenConnect currently supports
basic username/password, optional TLS client certificate, and optional multifactor
authentication token entry via the "tokeninfo" challenge/response mechanism (which
appears to be the most common mechanism by which Fortinet VPNs support multifactor
authentication). If you have access to a Fortinet VPN which uses other types of
authentication, please send information to <a href="mail.html">the mailing
list</a> so that we add support to OpenConnect.</p>

<p>The Fortinet protocol appears <i>not</i> to allow its
post-authentication cookie (as output by <tt>--authenticate</tt>) to
be used to reestablish a dropped connection. This means that if the
client loses its connection to the gateway (for example, due to a
network outage, or after roaming to a different physical adapter) a
new authentication will <i>always</i> be required. This is a substantial
design flaw which is not present in any of the other protocols
supported by OpenConnect; if you have access to a Fortinet VPN which
<i>can</i> automatically reconnect after a dropped connection,
please send information to <a href="mail.html">the mailing list</a>
so we can understand it better, and whether we can support this feature
on other Fortinet VPNs.</p>

<p>OpenConnect does not yet support the UDP transport for Fortinet, and
will use PPP over TCP for connectivity,
<a href="http://sites.inka.de/~W1011/devel/tcp-tcp.html">which is suboptimal
for performance</a>.</p>

	<INCLUDE file="inc/footer.tmpl" />
</PAGE>
