<PAGE>
	<INCLUDE file="inc/header.tmpl" />

	<VAR match="VAR_SEL_CONTRIBUTE" replace="selected" />
	<VAR match="VAR_SEL_CONTRIB_MITM" replace="selected" />
	<PARSE file="menu1.xml" />
	<PARSE file="menu2-contribute.xml" />

	<INCLUDE file="inc/content.tmpl" />

<h1>Observing VPN clients</h1>

<p>Most of the VPN <a href="protocols.html">protocols supported by
OpenConnect</a> are proprietary, undocumented, and in many cases
overly-complex, perhaps intentionally obfuscated.</p>

<p>In order to add support for <a
href="contribute.html#new-protocols">new protocols</a>, and sometimes
even to improve or update support for existing ones, it is often
necessary to observe existing clients and servers in order to
understand how they work.</p>

<h2>Observing TLS/SSL connections</h2>

<p>Modern VPN protocols almost always support a UDP-based transport
for tunneled packets, e.g. DTLS for the Cisco AnyConnect protocol, or
ESP for the GlobalProtect protocol. This is because <a
href="http://sites.inka.de/~W1011/devel/tcp-tcp.html">TCP over TCP is
very suboptimal</a> in terms of performance. However, most VPN
protocols also support TLS/SSL for connection initiation and as a
fallback, due to its universal availability even in highly filtered or
firewalled network environments. <b>It is typically more
straightforward and productive to start out by observing the TLS/SSL
side of a new VPN protocol, and saving the UDP-based transport for
later</b> (See <a
href="http://lists.infradead.org/pipermail/openconnect-devel/2016-October/004015.html">this
discussion thread</a> from the <a href="mail.html">mailing list</a>
during the initial work on the <a
href="globalprotect.html">GlobalProtect protocol</a>.)</p>

<p>The content of a TLS/SSL connection is end-to-end encrypted and
authenticated, and the session keys are normally kept only in memory
by the applications using these connections. Therefore, special
techniques are needed to decrypt traffic and observe the plaintext
bytes-on-the-wire of any TLS-based communications protocol.</p>

<p>There are more-or-less 3 possible techniques for decrypting
TLS-based communications and observing the plaintext. The first two
shown here are quite simply, but not universally usable; the
third is more complex but should be applicable to any TLS-based
VPN protocol.</p>

<h3>(1) Using SSLKEYLOGFILE</h3>

<p>If your VPN client is based on a standard TLS library and does not
disable this mechanism, it is likely the most straightforward way to
decrypt TLS traffic.</p>

<p>Most <a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_TLS_implementations">TLS
libraries</a> (including OpenSSL, GnuTLS, and LibNSS) support an
environment variable called <tt>SSLKEYLOGFILE</tt>, which will cause
applications using those libraries to write "premaster secrets" for
their TLS/DTLS sessions to a file.  This makes it straightforward to
automatically decrypt the traffic using the Wireshark network protocol
analyzer. Basically, you should run the VPN client that you're
observing with this environment variable set, run Wireshark on the
same computer, and configure Wireshark to use the resulting log file;
see <a href="https://wiki.wireshark.org/TLS#tls-decryption">Wireshark's
TLS decryption documentation for details.</a></p>

<p>Note that some proprietary VPN clients disable the
<tt>SSLKEYLOGFILE</tt> mechanism to prevent decryption of their
traffic, but many developers overlook this especially in early
releases of their client software.</p>

<h3>(2) Using server's RSA private key</h3>

<p>If you have access to the RSA private key of a VPN <i>server</i>
supporting the protocol you're observing (likely because you
administer such a VPN), and can use RSA key exchange, then you can
provide this RSA private key to Wireshark and automatically decrypt
TLS traffic to and from <i>this server</i> using Wireshark; again, see
<a href="https://wiki.wireshark.org/TLS#tls-decryption">Wireshark's
TLS decryption documentation for details and limitations.</a></p>

<p>This works because the RSA key exchange supported by TLS (re)uses
the server's private key for encryption of the ephemeral session keys,
unlike Diffie-Helman or Elliptic Curve Diffie-Helman exchanges which
do not. (<a href="https://security.stackexchange.com/a/35521">More
detailed explanation on StackExchange.</a>)</p>

<p>This lack of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forward_secrecy">forward
secrecy</a> of session keys is indeed why RSA key exchange has been
deprecated in TLS 1.2 and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transport_Layer_Security#Key_exchange_or_key_agreement">removed
in TLS 1.3</a>. However, most VPN servers and clients continue to
support TLS 1.2 or older with RSA key exchange for backwards
compatibility, so this is still a viable option for decrypting traffic
as of 2022.</p>

<h3>(3) MITM</h3>

<p>If you cannot use either of the above mechanisms, then you will
need to use the <a
href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">MITM
technique</a> to decrypt traffic to/from the VPN client you are
observing.</p>

<p>The basic idea is to convince the two peers of the TLS connection
(VPN client and server) that they are communicating directly with each
other via an end-to-end encrypted TLS session, when in fact each of
them is in fact communicating with an intermediary (the
"man-in-the-middle").  The intermediary creates two <i>separate</i>
TLS sessions: one between the real client and the intermediary, and
one between the intermediary and the real server. The intermediary can
inspect and modify traffic before relaying it between the the peers,
who continue to believe that they are communicating directly with each
other.</p>

<p>In order to MITM-capture the traffic from a typical proprietary VPN
client:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Use <a href="https://mitmproxy.org">mitmproxy</a>, running on
  Linux. (There are other similar tools available, but the rest of
  this document will assume you are running <tt>mitmproxy</tt> on
  Linux.)</li>

  <li>Set up a virtual machine and install the required operating and
  VPN client. (It is possible to do this using a physical system as
  well, but this will make transparent routing more complex.) We
  recommend:
  <ul>
    <li>Linux host OS with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel-based_Virtual_Machine">KVM/QEMU</a>
    as a hypervisor</li>
    <li>Guest/VM configured for <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/QEMU/Networking#User_mode_networking">user
    mode networking</a></li>
    <li>Assuming the guest is running Microsoft Windows as its OS, install <a href="https://access.redhat.com/articles/2488201">RedHat's
    paravirtualized I/O drivers</a> to improve performance.</li>
  </ul></li>

  <li><p>Run <tt>mitmproxy</tt> on the host system, and route traffic
  from the VM through it <i>transparently</i>, that is without setting
  an explicit proxy.</p><p>With KVM/QEMU and user-mode networking, this
  consists of setting the guest system's IPv4 gateway to
  <tt>10.0.2.2</tt> and setting up <tt>iptables</tt> rules on the
  Linux host to redirect traffic. (Described in more detail in
  <a href="https://docs.mitmproxy.org/stable/howto-transparent-vms">mitmproxy's
  guide to transparently proxying virtual machines</a>).</p></li>

  <li><p><b>Browse to the URL <a
  href="https://mitm.it">https://mitm.it</a> on the VM</b>; this is a
  special domain intercepted by <tt>mitmproxy</tt> itself.</p><p>The
  web page shown will help you verify that (a) the VM's traffic is
  really passing through MITMproxy and (b) the VM's operating system
  trusts <tt>mitmproxy</tt>'s certificates.</p></li>

  <li>Run the VPN client on the VM, and capture and study its traffic
  using <tt>mitmproxy</tt> (or <tt>mitmdump</tt>) on the host.</li>

  <li><p>The client and/or server may employ various mechanisms to detect
  MITM and shut down the MITM'ed connection. <b>Trick,
  bludgeon, or confuse the client and server into ignoring this</b>;
  see below for specific examples.</p><p>This usually works by
  sending a copy or hash/fingerprint of the server's TLS certificate
  as part of the in-band protocol data, and checking for differences
  from the certificate exchanged in the TLS handshake. </p></li>

  <li>Repeat these steps iteratively to understand how the VPN
  client's interaction with the VPN server works.</li>
</ol>

<p>In cases where your VPN client/server detect MITM'ed connections
and stop communicating (6), it's typically necessary to write a script
which will detect and rewrite in-band protocol data containing the
server's TLS certificate (or a hash/fingerprint of it). This requires
a recent version of <tt>mitmproxy</tt> containing <a
href="https://github.com/mitmproxy/mitmproxy/pull/1935">pull request
#1935</a> which was contributed by OpenConnect developers for this
purpose.</p>

<p>An example of such a script may be useful:
<a href="https://gitlab.com/dlenski/pangp-hacks/-/blob/master/gp_ssl_log.py">gp_ssl_log.py</a>.
This script works with <tt>mitmproxy</tt> or <tt>mitmdump</tt> to modify
traffic to/from with a GlobalProtect server; specifically it <a
href="https://gitlab.com/dlenski/pangp-hacks/-/blob/master/gp_ssl_log.py#L63-68">mangles
the <tt>&lt;root-ca&gt;</tt> XML tag</a> sent by GlobalProtect portal
servers, which GlobalProtect's official client software uses to verify
that certificates of servers it connects to. It can be used with
<tt>mitmdump</tt> as follows:</p>

<pre>
  ./mitmdump -vvv --tcp $YOUR_GP_SERVER_IP -s /path/to/gp_ssl_log.py --ssl-version-server all --insecure
</pre>

<h2>Documenting VPN protocols</h2>

<p>Sometimes it's most satisfying and productive to simply start
coding up support for a new protocol or feature in OpenConnect
itself. However, if you don't understand the structure of the
OpenConnect codebase well, this may make it difficult to explain and
discuss the code with more experienced developers.</p>

<p>Often it is very useful to take a step back and explain how the VPN
protocol works in more human-readable terms before implementing it in
OpenConnect's codebase.  Preparing a document that intersperses prose
explanations with captured traffic can aid in communication.  See
<a href="https://github.com/dlenski/openconnect/blob/master/PAN_GlobalProtect_protocol_doc.md">PAN_GlobalProtect_protocol_doc.md</a>,
(prepared during the implementation of the GlobalProtect protocol in
OpenConnect, and subsequently updated) for a complete example.</p>

<h2>Ask for help</h2>

<p>Ask on the <a href="mail.html">mailing list</a> for help with new
protocol implementations, or show us your code via Merge Requests
on GitLab.</p>

<INCLUDE file="inc/footer.tmpl" />
</PAGE>
